<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catalogve of superstitons innovations in the change of services and ceremonies, of presumptuous irregularities, and transgressions, against the Articles of Religion, Act of Parliament for uniformity, canons, advertisements, injunctions, and homilies and lastly, of sundry perjurious violations of the locall statutes of Durham Cathedrall church, which the dean and presendaries, and all other members of the said church, took their corporall oaths, to observe, and obey, at their admittance and installation, according to that in the 13. Chap. De admissione Canonicorum ... / opposed by Peter Smart ...</title>
            <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11779165</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11779165</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48966</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48966)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 548:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catalogve of superstitons innovations in the change of services and ceremonies, of presumptuous irregularities, and transgressions, against the Articles of Religion, Act of Parliament for uniformity, canons, advertisements, injunctions, and homilies and lastly, of sundry perjurious violations of the locall statutes of Durham Cathedrall church, which the dean and presendaries, and all other members of the said church, took their corporall oaths, to observe, and obey, at their admittance and installation, according to that in the 13. Chap. De admissione Canonicorum ... / opposed by Peter Smart ...</title>
                  <author>Smart, Peter, 1569-1652?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9-30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hunscott,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Durham Cathedral --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48966:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48966:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CATALOGVE OF SUPERSTITIOUS INNOVATIONS IN The change of Services and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; of preſumptuous irregularities, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, againſt the Articles of Religion, Act of Parliament for uniformity, Canons, Advertiſements, Injunctions, and Homilies.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly, Of ſundry perjurious Violations of the locall Statutes of <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall Church, which the Dean and Prebendaries, and all other Members of the ſaid Church, took their corporall Oaths, to obſerve, and obey, at their admittance and inſtallation, according to that in the 13. Chap. <hi>Deadmiſſione Canonicorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnes cujuſcunque nominis &amp; conditionis fuerit jurabunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Brought into <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall by Biſhop <hi>Neal,</hi> and the Dean, and Prebendaries of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>Oppoſed by <hi>Peter Smart,</hi> Prebendary of <hi>Durham,</hi> lately reſtored to his ſaid Prebend, All cenſures and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Commiſſioners and other Judges, being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed and Cancelled by the High Court of Parliament, after his eleven yeers impriſonment, and fourteen yeers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in the ſeverall High Commiſſions of <hi>Durham, London,</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> for Preaching againſt the Superſtitious Innovations in <hi>Durham,</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hunſcott.</hi> 1642</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48966:2"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48966:2"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Superſtitious Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the change of Services and Ceremonies; Of preſumptuous irregularities, and tranſgreſſions againſt the Articles of Religion, Act of Parliament for uniformity, Canons, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, Iujunctions, and Homilies, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nnovators in <hi>Durbam,</hi> offended againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in taking away the Communion-Table, and in place thereof, erecting an Altar contrary to the Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Tables in Churches, which commandeth Altars to be removed, and Communion-Tables, brought into all Churches, and Chappels, both Cathedrall and others, that uniformity might be obſerved.</p>
            <p>2. They likewiſe offended againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> in all her Church-Books (in which the word Altar for Communion-Table is never put,) I mean the new Teſtament, the Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer, the Injunctions, Canons, Articles of Religion, and Homilies; they offended I ſay, in that they give to the holy Table, the name of an Altar, it being no true Altar; not ſo much as the Image of an Altar, or having any likeneſſe, or reſemblance of an Altar.</p>
            <p>3. They offended in making it a brave and ſumptuous Altar, with much gay and gaudy ſuperſtitious and unlawfull furniture; whereas (according to the advertiſements, and eighty two Canon) it ought to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48966:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> a Table, not an Altar, a decent Table, not curiouſly carved, not gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beautified, painted, and guilded, to move admiration, nor vile filthy and rotten, to make it baſe and contemptible in the ſight of the people.</p>
            <p>4. They offended in making it of ſtone, whereas it ſhould be of Wood, and ſetting it upon ſtone Pillars, or upon a Wall; whereas it ſhould ſtand upon a frame, according to the Injunctions, <hi>Can. de Ae<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ituis Eccleſiarum,</hi> And the Latine Canon which ſaith, <hi>Curabunt Menſam ex aſſeribus compoſitè junct<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, quae adminiſtrationi ſacro-ſancte communionis inſeruiat,</hi> and practiſe of <hi>Durham,</hi> and other Cathedrall and Pariſh Churches, ſince the reformation, 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> when ſtone Altars were demoliſhed, becauſe they were unmoveable, faſtned to the ground, and ſo heavy, that twenty men could not bear one ſtone Altar, but they ſhould be light and portable, for it is the Deacons Office to carry, or remoue the Table, and how can it be portable, if it be like to <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Altar, on ſtone columes, or Wormeth Altar, on a ſtone Wall; and how can the Deacons do their Office in removing the Table from place to place, as occaſion ſerveth, and our Church enjoyneth; which is unpoſſible, if it be of Marble ſtone<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and a double Table as <hi>Durham</hi> is, ſo heavy as a Wain-load of ſtones, and faſtned to the ground alſo.</p>
            <p>5. They impudently tranſgreſſed, eſpecially in ſome Pariſh Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, in not placing the holy Table where morning Prayer, and evening Prayer are appointed to be ſaid, but at the Eaſt end of the Church or Chancell, whereno part of evening Prayer is ever ſaid in any Church at an Altar or Table, but in Pariſh Churches; where there are long and narrow Chancels, the people in the Body of the Church neither hear nor ſee the Prieſt at his Altar in the Eaſt, and conſequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be edified.</p>
            <p>Alſo in Cathedrall Churches, where the Table is placed ſo far from the Congregation, the Miniſter officiating thereat, cannot ſo well be heard, nor the people ſo well be edified, as when the Table ſtandeth in the Body of the Church, or Quire, neer amongſt the people.</p>
            <p>6. Innovators in <hi>Durbam</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> have notoriouſly tranſgreſſed againſt the Book of common Prayer, both in Cathedrall and Pariſh Churches and Chappells, in ſetting the Communion Table with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide toward the North, ſo that the Miniſter cannot ſtand at the North ſide, as the Rubrick enjoyns him to do, and as the cuſtome is of all Miniſters officiating.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48966:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>7. Innovators in <hi>Durham</hi> and <hi>York</hi> have grievouſly offended in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſly, and maintaining, That Prieſts, Sacrifices, and Altars are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently uſed for Miniſters, Sacraments, and Communion Tables in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for thoſe things are indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, which are uſed <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miſcuè,</hi> as <hi>Synonimous</hi> words of the ſame ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication are uſed commonly.</p>
            <p>But our Church Liturgy uſeth not the words Prieſt, Sacrifice, and Altar indifferently, and ſo commonly as the words Miniſter, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Communion Table;</p>
            <p>For Altar is never mentioned in our Liturgie, but the Lords Table, and Lords Boord; nor Sacrament is ever tearmed a Sacrifice in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy; for at the Communion all that receive are appointed to ſay, <hi>Accept, O Lord, this our Sacrifice of praiſe and thanksgiving:</hi> And again, not the Miniſter alone, but all the Communicants muſt ſay, <hi>We offer and preſent unto thee, O Lord, our ſouls and Bodies to be an holy and lively Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> neither is the word Prieſt ever ſo much as once mentioned in the Text of our Liturgy, ſave onely in the Rubrick, which are rules and directions how to uſe the Liturgy:</p>
            <p>As for example, In the Abſolution, <hi>God hath given power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment to his Miniſters</hi> (not Prieſts) <hi>to declare and pronounce to his people, being penitent, the Abſolution and Remiſſion of their ſinnes:</hi> And in the Letany, <hi>That it will pleaſe thee to illuminate all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church, &amp;c.</hi> And another place, <hi>Endues by Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with righteouſneſſe</hi> (not Prieſts) becauſe the word Prieſt, implyes a Sacrifice, as ſaith Biſhop <hi>Latimer;</hi> and it is never uſed in the Word of God, for a Miniſter of the Goſpel: ſo that by uſing the words Altar, Prieſt, Sacrifice, they ſpeak not the language of their Mother the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. They offended in oppoſing the Fathers, and the primitive Church, againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the grave and learned Biſhops which reformed the ſame, in defence of Altars, Prieſts, Sacrifices, &amp;c. which they preferre before Communion Tables, Miniſters, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor Morton,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> in his Apologie, pag. 165. ſaith, Primitive antiquity (as hath been confeſſed by Papiſts themſelves) did abſtain from the names of Prieſt, Altar, and Sacrifices, tearming them according to the tenor of the new Teſtament, Elders, or Biſhops, Tables and Euchariſts.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48966:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In the after times, the Fathers preſumed to take a greater liberty of ſpeech; but they never meant to defend ſuch popiſh ſacriledge, as is the having of Prieſts, Sacrifices, and Altars: And becauſe ages more degenerating did ſet as it were a Byas upon the phraſes Prieſts, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Altar (which had been uſed by the Fathers improperly) to draw them to a proper ſignification, flat contrary to their firſt Inſtitution; therefore did Proteſtants wiſh, That thoſe ancient Fathers had rather contained themſelves within their more ancient bounds, than that their liberty of ſpeech ſhould have occaſioned in Romaniſts that prodigall error in Doctrine. Thus much ſaith Doctor <hi>Morton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9. They notoriouſly offended in removing the Font ſo often from the ancient uſuall place where heretofore it ſtood, contrary to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, <hi>The Font ſhall not be removed;</hi> and the 81 Canon, <hi>The Font ſhall ſtand in the ancient uſuall place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10. They offended highly in adoring the Altar, falſly ſo called; for when it is gorgeouſly adorned with brave and rich Furniture, and ſet up on high at top of the Quire or Chancell, removed from the baſe and prophane multitude, as they account them, and carrying a greater Majeſty than it had, being a plain Communion Table, ſtanding in the Body of the Church, then they bowed down to it, and worſhipped it, more than ever the papiſts did, making it thereby an execrable Idoll; they bow down, I ſay, their bodies before the ſame Altar, and towards no other thing or place in the Church, as if it were the moſt holy thing the Church of God hath, (as Doctor <hi>Duncomb</hi> blaſphemouſly writeth, in his Determination) holyer than the Bible it ſelf, to which none make legs, or bow their bodies.</p>
            <p>11. They have offended in contradicting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and endamaging our reformed Religion, in not defacing nor aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing monuments of Idolatry, but repairing, adorning, beautifying, and multiplying them, more than ever they were in time of popery, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the 23 Injunction, in which, charge is given for the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things ſuperſtitious.</p>
            <p>That Candleſticks, Pictures, Paintings, and all manner of Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Idolatry be taken away, utterly extinct, and deſtroyed. So that there remain no memory of the ſame in Walls, Windows, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>Item,</hi> In the Articles of the firſt yeer of the Queens viſitation, 1559. The ſecond Article enquireth, whether Candleſticks, Images,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48966:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Pictures, and other Monuments of Idolatry, and Superſtition, be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: Hereby it appeareth that the intention of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was at the reformation thereof; from Popiſh Superſtition, and Idolatry, that Maſſing Copes, and other Altar Cloaths, embroydered with Images: That Candleſticks, Tapers, Croſſes, Crucifixes, &amp;c. being once ejected, muſt not be brought in again, and ſet upon the Communion Table, or in Windows above the Table, as is done in <hi>Durham,</hi> and other Churches adjoyning.</p>
            <p>12. They offended in rejecting the Homilies, and Injunctions, and conſequently the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they condemn Images, Altars, and other ſuperfluous ornaments.</p>
            <p>The Homily of the place, and time of prayer, hath theſe words of a woman, ſaying, to her neighbour at the firſt reformation of Churches in <hi>England;</hi> Alas, alas, what ſhall we now do at Church, ſince all the Saints are taken away, ſeeing all the goodly fights we were wont to have are gone, ſeeing we cannot have the like piping, and chanting, and playing on the Organs that we had before. But dearly beloved, ſaith the Homily, we ought greatly to rejoyce, and give God thanks, that our Churches are delivered from all theſe things which diſpleaſed God ſo ſore; but now, thoſe abominations which were taken away at <hi>Durham,</hi> are reſtored again with great advantage.</p>
            <p>13. They offended in calling their ſuperſtitious Trinkets, Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church, which our Church diſalloweth, and condemneth, as being diſgracements of Religion, and abominations in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Thus ſaith the Homily againſt the perill of Idolatry, and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious decking of Churches. The Lords holy Name ought to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon by publike prayer, and thankſgiving; his holy Sacraments ought duly and reverently to be adminiſtred, not gaudily, flauntingly, theatrically, hiſtriorically; due reverence is ſtirred up in the hearts of the godly by the confideration of thoſe true ornaments of the houſe of God, and not by any outward Ceremonies, or coſtly and glorious deckings of the ſaid Houſe or Temple of the Lord, as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Orantium in ſe retorquent aſpectum, impediunt affectum,</hi> Such glorious ſpectacles draw away from God, the minde of them that pray, and they hinder holy affections, or meditations.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48966:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Praetendunt ornatum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Heming<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi>) in his <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> ſpeaking of Images, <hi>Si illi ornat<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adjunctum ſit ullu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> periculum, ſit maledictus.</hi> They pretend that they are ſet up for Ornaments, but cu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed be ſuch Ornaments, to which the perill of Idolatry is joyned; And again, <hi>Spiritus Sanctus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ezekiel, Chr. 20. Vocat Idola abominationes ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, ſed puluis &amp; ciuis ea vocat ornamenta oculorum,</hi> The holy Ghoſt calls Images the abhomination of the eyes, but man that is but duſt and aſhes, calls them the ornaments of the eyes, and then he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Verus ornatus Templorum, utilis &amp; Deo, gratus eſt, concio, cantio, oratio, communio &amp; non haec quae vel impediunt vol vitiant,</hi> The true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the Church profitable to men, and acceptable to God, is, the preaching of Gods Word, the ſinging of Pſalms, the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, and Prayer, and not ſuch things as do hinder and defile the ſame.</p>
            <p>14. They have offended againſt their Mother, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in taking away the ten Commandments, where they placed their Altar; for having caſt out the decent Communion Table at the ſame time, they ſent away into the Countrey the Decalogue fairly written in golden Letters, contrary to the expreſſe words of the 82. Canon, and practiſe of all our Churches.</p>
            <p>The ten Commandments ſhall be ſet upon the Eaſt end of every Church or Chapell where the people may beſt ſee and read the ſame; So they were placed in <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall, very fairly written, and hanging upon the Wall, till the Lords Table was taken away, and a brave ſumptuous Altar daily adored by all ſorts of people, ſpecially, Prieſts and Clerks, with bowing down their bodies before it.</p>
            <p>Till (I ſay) a glorious high Altar was erected with Crucifixes, and other Images of Saints and Angels, even of the Trinity it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Which Idols (as the Church of <hi>England</hi> calls them in her Homilies) could not endure the preſence of Gods ſecond Commandment, which forbids Images and Idolatry; and much more reaſon had they to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Decalogue out of their ſight, ſince the fourth Commandment alſo was by them abrogated, which commandeth the obſervation of the Sabbath, <hi>Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day, the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt do no manner of work.</hi> At the end of the fourth Commandment, our Church enjoyneth the people to kneel down, and ſay, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, and incline
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48966:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> our hearts to keep this Law,</hi> What Law? The Law for obſerving the Chriſtian Sabbath; which word Doctor <hi>Linſell</hi> ſaid, My ſtomack riſeth when I hear Sabbath, call it no more Sabbath; And Biſhop <hi>Neal</hi> ſaid at his viſitation in <hi>Durham,</hi> I ſee no reaſon but that the Feſtivall day of a Saint, may be preferred before Sunday, what is Sunday?</p>
            <p>15. They have ridiculouſly and ſuperſtitiouſly offended in the uſe of Copes, and other ſuperſtitious Veſtments, falſely called Copes, at unlawfull times and places.</p>
            <p>And they continued even till this time, 1642. in the ſame abuſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admoniſhed and taught the truth, they will not amend, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their errour.</p>
            <p>The 24. Canon ſaith thus, in all Cathedrall and Colligiat Churches, the holy Communion ſhall be adminiſtred by the Biſhop or a Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary, the principall Miniſter uſing a decent Cope, and being aſſiſted by the Epiſtoler and Goſpeller agreeably, according to the advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments publiſhed, <hi>Anno 7. Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The advertiſements made by Commiſſioners authorized, under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith thus:</p>
            <p>At the adminiſtration of the holy Communion in Cathedrall and Collegiat Churches, the principall Miniſter ſhall uſe a Cope with the Epiſtoler and Goſpeller agreeably, and at all other prayers at the Communion Table, to uſe no Copes but Surpleſſes; The 45. Canon ſaith the ſame, <hi>When there is no Communion, it ſhall be ſufficient to wear Surpleſſes.</hi> By this it is manifeſt, That the Copes muſt be decent, and they muſt never be uſed, ſave only at the adminiſtration of the holy Communion.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Durham</hi> Innovators did ſay their ſecond Service daily when there was no Communion at their Altar, and after every Sermon, one of the Prieſts did put on a Cope, to ſay, two or three Prayers at the Altar, not ſuffering the Miniſter to diſmiſſe the Congregation with bleſſing of Gods peace as was wont to be done in <hi>Durham,</hi> and all other Cathedralls of <hi>England,</hi> till very lately ſome new fangled Deans, and ignorant Canons, abſurdly have imitated <hi>Durhams</hi> fooleries.</p>
            <p>16. They offended in uſing, and juſtifying him that uſed a Cope in the Pulpit, a Hood being appointed, and ſitting in his Stall in a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48966:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Cope at time of divine Service and Sermon; at which times, Hoods are alwayes commanded to be worn by Graduates, which are never put on with Copes, and Copes are alwayes forbidden, ſave only at the adminiſtration of the holy Communion.</p>
            <p>This was done in <hi>Durham,</hi> contrary to the example of all Churches, either popiſh or Reformed; contrary alſo to the expreſſe words of the Canon and Injunctions. In the 25 Canon thus we reade, <hi>In the time of Divine Service in all Cathedrall and Collegiate Churches, Deans and Prebendaries being Graduates, ſhall dayly, at the times of Prayers and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, wear with their Surplices ſuch hoods as are agreeable to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Advertiſement ſaith the ſame, <hi>Item, That the Dean and Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries wear a Surplice with a Silk Hood in the Quire, and when they preach in the Cathedrall or Collegiate Church, to wear their Hoods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Burg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn,</hi> the firſt ſetter up of Altars, and introducer of other popiſh Ceremonies in that Countrey, having taken three Degrees in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> offended thrice in wearing a Cope without his Hood; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Hood he preached twice; and once ſate in his ſtall in a Cope when he preached not, as if he had been ſome Sir <hi>John</hi> lack-latine, or ſimple petty-Canon.</p>
            <p>17. They offended both in uſing ſumptuous Copes glittering with Images; and among the reſt, of the bleſſed Trinity; God the Father, in the likeneſſe of an old man; God the Son, in the likeneſſe of a young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er man; the holy Ghoſt, in the ſimilitude of a Dove, wrought upon red Velvet with Gold, Silver, and Pearl; one of which was taken from a Maſſe-prieſt.</p>
            <p>As alſo in uſing ſcurvie, py-bald, curtal'd, and ridiculous Veſtments, falſly called Copes (being indeed very fools coats) at the Communion Table, and that dayly at the Adminiſtration of the holy Communion; whereas by the aforeſaid 24 Canon, a decent Cope is onely command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and by the Latine Canon all Veſtments defiled with ſuperſtition are forbidden: in the latine Canon <hi>de officio Decani,</hi> thus we are taught, <hi>Nullus ex ordine Eccleſiaſtico quocunque nomine cenſeatur, utetur ulla ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte ſuperſtitione contaminata;</hi> No Eccleſiaſticall perſon, by what name ſoever he be called, ſhall uſe the gray <hi>Amice</hi> (as they call it) or any other Veſture defiled with like ſuperſtition.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48966:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>18 They have wickedly tranſgreſſed againſt the 49. Injunction, in abuſing the laudible Science of Muſicke every day, and every Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice without underſtanding of the people, and edification.</p>
            <p>The 49. Injunction willeth and commandeth the laudible Science of Muſick be ſo preſerved, that the ſame in any part of Service, he not ſo abuſed in the Church, that thereby the Common Prayer ſhould be the worſe underſtood of the hearers. That there be a modeſt and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ſong, ſo uſed in all parts of the Common Praiers in the Church, that the ſame may be as plainly underſtood, as if it were read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinging. And although one Hymne of more exquiſite Muſick, in the beginning or end of Common Prayers may be ſung; yet reſpect muſt be had, that the ſentence of the Hymne may be underſtood and perceived.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this Injunction, our <hi>Durhamers</hi> have been ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon piping and ſinging, that in ſtead of the Morning Prayer at 6. of the clock, which was wont to be read diſtinctly and plainly, for Schollers, and Artificers before they begin their work, they brought in a ſolemne Service, with ſinging and Organs, Sackbuts and Cornets, little whereof could be underſtood of the people, neither would they ſuffer the Sacrament to be adminiſtred without a continuall noiſe of Muſick both inſtrumentall and vocal, to the great diſturbance of thoſe holy actions.</p>
            <p>19 They offended in multiplying unlawfull Anthemes, and diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing lawfull Pſalms-ſinging by the whole Congregation, before and after Sermons; according to the cuſtome of all Cathedrall and Collegiate Churches, and of <hi>Durham</hi> it ſelf, before Doctor <hi>Coſins</hi> and other of Biſhop <hi>Neals</hi> Chaplains became Cannons of that Church; which unlawfull forbidding of Pſalms to be ſung in a vulgar tune, according to the cuſtome of all other Churches: they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to this preſent yeer, 1642.</p>
            <p>20 They offended in ſinging the <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> not after the manner of diſtinct reading, as the aforeſaid Injunction commands, and as that which is called the Apoſtles Creed is ſung, yet forcing the people with brawling in the time of Divine Service, to ſtand up upon their feet, all the time that it is ſung though they underſtand nothing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they perceive, whether it be a prayer or a Creed contrary to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48966:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Rubrick and Injunction, and 18 <hi>Cannon</hi> which injoyneth the people to ſtand up, when the Apoſtles Creed is ſaid, ſaying with the Miniſter in an audible voice, which none can do when the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed is ſung by the whole Quire, with all their muſical inſtruments.</p>
            <p>21 They offended in taking pipers and ſingers for aſſiſtants, at the Adminiſtration of the holy Communion: which are diſturbers ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is an Innovation in <hi>Durham,</hi> begun there when Doctor <hi>Coſins</hi> was made Prebendary of that Church; for both in <hi>England,</hi> and all other reformed Churches all are commanded to depart which do not communicate.</p>
            <p>22. They offended in chanting in the Quire amongſt ſinging men and children; which is a baſe employment, for Maior Cannons, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries, and Preachers, amongſt whom it is a thing unaccuſtomed, and unlawfull, when they ſit in their Prebendall ſtals diſallowed by Biſhop <hi>Howſon</hi> their Dioceſan in his Viſitation, and forbidden by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, who ſaith, <hi>Prohibitum est, ne quis in Eccleſia cantet niſi inferiores ordines ut pote ſubdiaconi; Diaconi vero lectioni &amp; praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni incumbant.</hi> It is forbidden (ſaith he) that any chant in the Churches but men of meane degree, none above Subdeacons, but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or Deacons, muſt apply themſelves to reading and preaching, for that makes moſt for the peoples edification, to which all muſt be done.</p>
            <p>In old time, <hi>Omnes ſimul pſallebant in Eccleſia,</hi> all Chriſtians did ſing together in the Church; yet now, <hi>Soli Clerici canunt,</hi> the Clerks onely ſing, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>li. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. de verbi Dei, cap. 16. &amp; lib. 1. de bonis operibus, cap.</hi> 16. Yea though the Papiſts confeſſe, that it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in commandment by St. <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bineus</hi>) that the faithfull in their Aſſemblies, ſhould praiſe God together with heart and voyce by ſinging Pſalmes, yet they tell us (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) that <hi>Eccleſiaſticae inſtitutione optime proviſum eſt, ne praeter certos ad hoc inſcriptos alii in Eccl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſia canerent.</hi> It is excellently well provided for by the Orders of the Church, that none ſhould ſing but a ſet number appointed for that purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Prieſts, Clerks, Singingmen and Quiriſters.</p>
            <p>23 The moſt impudent and moſt unlawfull Innovation that ever was ſeen in any Cathedrall Church of <hi>England;</hi> was that of taking
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48966:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> away the Morning Prayer at 6. of the clock, which had continued above ſixty yeers; and putting in the place thereof, the ordinary Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Service appointed to be ſaid at ten of the clock, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued about two yeers.</p>
            <p>Injunctions were given <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptember 25 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Eli<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Eures,</hi> Doctor <hi>Sands,</hi> and others, Commiſſioners authoriſed under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> to the Dean and Chapter of <hi>Durham,</hi> and to all other Miniſters of that Church, to be obſerved by every of them, in their offices and degrees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the advancement of Gods glory.</p>
            <p>The 10. Injunction is this, conſiſting of 5 clauſes, the firſt, that you ſhall have your Divine Service at due or convenient houres in your Church.</p>
            <p>2 And that you ſhall (beſides your ordinary Morning Prayer and Service) have every working day, at 6. of the clock in the morning, the Common Prayer with the Engliſh Letany, and Suffrages, inſtead, and in place of the morrow Maſſe.</p>
            <p>3 To the intent, that the Schollers of the Grammer Schoole, and other well diſpoſed perſons may daily reſort thereto.</p>
            <p>4 And that ſome be appointed weekly as it ſhall come to their courſe: either ſuch as were appointed for the morrow Maſſe, or elſe ſome of the petty Cannons.</p>
            <p>5 And that to be done in ſome convenient place of the Church.</p>
            <p>24 The foreſaid Morning Prayer at ſix of the clock, our Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Durham,</hi> might not alter or diſanull.</p>
            <p>1 Becauſe it was ordained and eſtabliſhed by lawfull Authority, of the Soveraigne Prince and Parliament, under the great Seal of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> in the generall reformation of the Church, which private men without authoritie, might not take away nor change, without the danger of excommunication and deprivation, for their impudent ſawcineſſe, in rebelliouſly withſtanding the Kings Laws.</p>
            <p>2 Becauſe it was contrary to the cuſtome of <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall, which had continued ever ſince the firſt yeer of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1559. till the ſecond yeer of our Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charles;</hi> to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of which cuſtome, all <hi>Durham</hi> Prebends, take expreſly their corporall oath when they are inſtalled.</p>
            <p>3 Becauſe it is contrary to all Cathedrall Churches in <hi>England,</hi> (as Biſhop <hi>Howſon</hi> ſaid) which Cathedrals ſtill retain their Morning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48966:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Prayers, plainly read by one Miniſter, with a Pſalm in the end, in a vulgar tune, which all the Congregation may ſing together.</p>
            <p>4 Becauſe theſe Injunctions being made for the advancement of Gods glory, the taking away of this Morning Prayer diſtinctly ſaid, is the hindrance of Gods glory, with the devotion and edification of Scholers; and other people for whom it was ordained: without which edifying knowledge, no ſervice can be acceptable to God, either in Cathedrall or Pariſh Churches.</p>
            <p>25 In the foreſaid Injunction for 6 a clock Prayer, 5 clauſes are conteined; againſt every one of which our new fangled <hi>Durhamers,</hi> have notoriouſly offended, they have overthrown and turned upſide down, the whole frame and form of all forenoon Services, confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ordinary Service at 10 a clock with the 6 a clock Prayer, and bringing in a new found ſecond Service to be ſaid alone, without a firſt at the ordinarie accuſtomed houres of the day, by which they have depraved the whole book of Common Prayer, and the Rubricks thereof.</p>
            <p>26 Concerning the firſt of which five, in <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall, the Divine Service called in this Injunction the ordinary Morning Praier, hath not been kept at convenient and due houres, the uſuall time whereof was all the time of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> between the houres of nine and eleven; but our brainſick Innovators of <hi>Durham,</hi> removed the ordinary Service to 8 a clock, and ſo it continued about a yeer, and all that time, they had 3 forenoon Services, one at 6. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at 8. and a third at 10. of the clock, afterwards upon better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice (becauſe three Services in one forenoon were tedious) they took quite away the plain and beſt Morning Prayer, appointed by this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and put in place thereof, the ordinary Divine Service, and called the people thereunto, by the ringing of three Bels, to which not 3 perſons uſually reſorted, eſpecially in Winter, time, and dark mornings.</p>
            <p>27 The ordinary Morning Prayer (called the Mattens and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service in the foreſaid Injunction) which appoints it to be ſaid at due and convenient houres, that is between the houres of nine and eleven, (according to the cuſtome and practiſe of all Churches) is that which is ordained in the book of Common Prayer, the Rubricks pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the manner of ſaying the ſame, for time, place, order, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48966:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> of rights and Ceremonies without alteration; according to the Cannon of our Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervabunt ordines &amp; ritus deſoriptos in libro publicar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m precum, tam in legendis ſacris Scripturis, &amp; precibus dicendis, quam etiam in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations Sacramentorum: ut nov<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> detrahant aliquid, neve addant, neve de materia, neve de forma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the 14. Cannon ſaith, all Miniſters ſhall obſerve the orders and Ceremonies preſcribed in the book of Common Prayer, without either adding or diminiſhing any thing in matter or form.</p>
            <p>Our ſeditious Innovators of <hi>Durham</hi> have not obſerved the orders and rights, preſcribed in the book of Common Prayer; but they have added, diminiſhed, and altred the whole form of Divine Service, and two yeers together they have had no ordinary Morning Service, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rubricks.</p>
            <p>28 For 2 yeers together from 1627. till 1629. our <hi>Durham</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Coſin</hi> and his Aſſociates, would not ſuffer any ordinary Morning Prayer to be ſaid at the due and uſuall time, between 9 and 11, in the place where Evening Prayer was duely ſaid; but every day, working dayes, and holy dayes, they went to the Altar (as they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it) to ſay a ſecond Service, ſo they call the Communion Service, which is no part of the ordinary Morning Prayer; as appeareth by the laſt Rubrick before the Letanie, and before that which they call the ſecond Service, Thus endeth the order of Morning and Evening Prayer throughout the yeer.</p>
            <p>Neither is the place where their Altar ſtands, the accuſtomed place, for ſaying any Divine Service, being at the Eaſt end of the Quire or Chancell, ſo farre in ſome Churches from the Congregation, that they can neither ſee the Miniſter, nor hear what he ſaith, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſo well as they do the Evening Prayer, ſaid in the uſuall place among them.</p>
            <p>29 The firſt Rubrick, in the book of Common Prayer, is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The order where Morning and Evening Prayer ſhall be uſed and ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Morning and Evening Prayer ſhall be uſed in the accuſtomed place of the Church, Chappell, or Chancell. And the Chancels ſhall remain as they have done in times paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Rubrick our <hi>Durham</hi> Innovators have violated ſundry waies, for here we ſee one place is appointed for Morning and Evening
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48966:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Prayer; not two places, one for Morning, and another for Evening Prayer.</p>
            <p>Evening Prayer hath been uſed in the accuſtomed place, in which it is alwayes ſaid in the midſt of the Quire. This alteration our irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Durhamers</hi> made themſelves, without the determination of the Ordinarie, who by the 14 Cannon is limited, that he may do nothing whereby edification may be hindred, and how can the people be edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, when they cannot hear the Miniſter, as is done in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Burgoyns</hi> Church at <hi>Warmoth,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>Again, whereas the Rubrick ſaith, Chancels ſhall remain as they have done in times paſt; our new fangled <hi>Durhamers,</hi> and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Prieſts (following their example) have made <hi>Cancellos inter Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellos,</hi> Chancels within Chancels, that is, an Incloſure, to divide their Altar Eaſtward from the Quire, as the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with curtains from the reſt of the Temple; who ever heard of 2 Chancels in one Church, till <hi>Durhamers</hi> invented it? contrary to this Rubrick and the example of all Churches in <hi>England</hi> in former times. So that they have a holy Church, a more holy Chancell, and at the Eaſt end thereof a moſt holy incloſure, where the Altar muſt ſtand, unto which no man or woman may have acceſſe but Prieſts onely.</p>
            <p>30 Another Rubrick ſaith, <hi>Then ſhall follow certain Pſalms in order, as they be appointed in the Table made for that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And another Rubrick ſaith, <hi>Then ſhall be read 2 Leſſons diſtinctly, with a loud voice that the people may hear; the firſt of the Old Teſtament, the ſecond of the New, like as they be appointed in the Kalender.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Miniſter that readeth the Leſſons, ſtanding, and turning him ſo, as he may be beſt heard of all that be preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Pſalms nor Chapters were read, either of the old or new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is a principall part of Divine Service) by our <hi>Durham</hi> Innovators for the ſpace of two yeers, and conſequently they had no ordinary Morning Service in their Cathedrall in the uſuall place, time, and form, as is preſcribed in the book of Common Prayer, Cannons, Injunctions, and Act of Parliament for Uniformity, which commands all Churches to be uniform; unto none of which <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall was agreeable in their Morning Services.</p>
            <p>31 The Act of Parliament for Uniformity hath theſe words: <hi>If any perſon, or Miniſter, in any Cathedrall, or pariſh Church, ſhall by open
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48966:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> fact, or deed, or by threatning, compell any to ſing or ſay, any common or open prayer, otherwiſe or in any other manner, or form, then is mentioned, in the book of Common Prayer, let him be indicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again in the ſame Act, no rite, order, form, or manner, at Mattens, or Even ſong, may be uſed in Cathedrall, or Pariſh Churches, but that which is appointed in the book of Common Prayer.</p>
            <p>The form of Morning prayer, was altred in <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall, by dividing it, into 2 parts, to be ſaid at two diſtinct times.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the Rubricks with ſundry Cannons, and Injunctions, have been violated, and broken by means of that diviſion.</p>
            <p>Many rites, and ceremonies, have been changed, &amp; unlawfully uſed.</p>
            <p>Men have been injoyned, at forbidden times, to weare unlawfull veſtments, condemned by our Church; ſome have been compelled with threatning and penalties to obey their unlawfull commands: As was evidently ſeen in the morning Prayer, which by the Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and cuſtome of 60 yeers continuance, was ſaid in a place appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereunto, by one petty Cannon alone, plainly, diſtinctly, and briefly to be ended at ſeven a clock.</p>
            <p>But new fangled <hi>Durhamers</hi> would have their new deviſed morning prayer, to be ſaid, and ſung<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſolemnly in the Quire, with all the voices of men and children, and muſicall inſtruments, whom they forced; to be preſent, at that unlawfull Service, and there to abide till all was done at 8 a clock, whereby they have deſerved many wayes to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, and for their contumacy deprived of all their livings, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Statute. In that being often admoniſhed, they would not amend for the ſpace of two yeers.</p>
            <p>32 But the moſt notorious Innovation, and moſt contrary to the foreſaid Act of Uniformitie, was that which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Coſin</hi> and his Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates took up at <hi>Durham</hi> about the yeer 1626. to go in a Cope to the Altar to ſay 2. or 3. prayers after every Sermon, which is a ſtrange ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, not mentioned in the book of Common Prayer, or Cannons, and conſequently forbidden.</p>
            <p>They would not ſuffer the Preacher to diſmiſſe the Congregation, with the bleſſing of Gods peace; as was wont to be done in <hi>Durham,</hi> and all other Churches of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They alledge for themſelves, the Rubrick after the <hi>Nicene Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After the Creed, if there be no Sermon, ſhall follow one of the Homilies, ſet forth by common Authority. And after ſuch Sermon, Homily, or exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48966:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Curate ſhall declare unto the people, whether there be any holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, or faſting dayes in the weeke following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And earnestly exhort them to remember the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Rubrick makes nothing for this fond Innovation, for it ſaith, After the Creed, if there be no Sermon, ſhall follow one of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. And then it ſaith, after ſuch Sermon, Homily, or Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Curate ſhall declare whether therebe any holidayes, or faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes.</p>
            <p>Here is a contradiction, or rather a nonſence, if the words be no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rightly underſtood.</p>
            <p>If there be no Sermon, and then, After ſuch Sermon, Homily, or Exhortation, what meaneth this?</p>
            <p>After ſuch Sermon, if there be no Sermon, the meaning of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick is plain, and the practiſe of all our Churches expound it, when there is no Communion, if there be no Sermon preached in the pulpit, the Curate being no preaching Miniſter, ſhall read an Homily or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; which Homily is termed a Sermon, not preached in the pulpit on any text of Scripture, but read as the reſt of the Service by the Curate, with no conceived prayer, or Pſalms ſung before or after the Homily: and then the Curate when the Homily is done, muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as the Rubrick directs him, to declare to the people, whether there be any holidayes the week following: and he muſt exhort them, to remember the poore, ſaying one or more of theſe ſentences.</p>
            <p>Now in what Cathedrall Church doth any Curate after Sermon, warne holidayes, or faſting dayes, or read any ſentence to exhort the people to make any collection for the poore?</p>
            <p>But every Preacher in a Cathedrall Church goeth up to the pulpit, taketh a text of Scripture, hath a Pſalme ſung, and maketh a prayer, before the Sermon; Which Sermon being done, concludeth with a prayer, he ſitteth down in the pulpit till the Pſalme be ended, and then ſtanding up, he diſmiſſeth the congregation with the bleſſing of Gods peace.</p>
            <p>Thus the Reformers of the Church underſtood their own Rubrick, and this hath been the practiſe of all Churches of <hi>England;</hi> till lately fantaſticall Innovators in <hi>Durham,</hi> changed and corrupted the whole form, and faſhion of our Church Service: and other Churches igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly and ſuperſtitiouſly have lately begun to imitate <hi>Durham,</hi> in the ſame ridiculous Innovations.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48966:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>33 They have offended in preaching and defending them that did preach againſt the religion eſtabliſhed, &amp; impudently traducing vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and diſgracing the grave and learned reformers of our Church, as Doctor <hi>Coſin</hi> did in his Sermon of the Parable of the Tares, That the Reformers of our Church when they took away the M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, they marr'd all religion and the ſervice of God, they called it a reformation, but it was indeed a deformation, and Doctor <hi>Linſell</hi> ſaid that the Reformers of our Church were ignorant Calviniſticall Biſhops, contrary to the advertiſement: no perſon ſhall preach any matter tending to diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or to the derogation of the religion, and doctrine received.</p>
            <p>34. They offended in altering orders eſtabliſhed, and ceremonies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and taking upon them to make new orders for the obſervation of unlawfull ſermons &amp; ceremonies without the Kings authority under the Great Seale of England, for which preſumption they are excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, though they pretend the Biſhops authority to whom they give tranſcendent authority, which is notwithſtanding limited by the locall ſtatutes of Durham Church, and by the Cannons both old and new: his office is aſſigned to preach and to ſee that the Church Service and Sacraments be rightly adminiſtred as is preſcribed in the Common Prayer; he may not hinder preaching by preferring petty ceremonies and ſolemne ſervices with piping and ſinging before Sermons, nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt with unlawfull orders and new rites both Service and Sacraments according to the firſt Latin Canon. 1571.</p>
            <p>35 They offended in making <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> a Creed, and making the people to ſtand when it is ſaid, it being no Creed, but a prayer. At which they are enjoyned to kneele, as likewiſe forcing the people to ſtand, when the Nicene Creed was ſung, and to kneele when ſome prayer is ſung. Though the people could not underſtand whether they were pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or Creed.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Article of religion <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tribus Symbolis</hi> acknowledgeth but three Creeds, to be ſaid in Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> the Nicene Creed, the Creed of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the Apoſtles Creed. Innovators in <hi>Durham</hi> have added a fourth Creed, <hi>Glory be to the Father, to the Sonne, &amp;c.</hi> and they enjoyned the Ceremonie of ſtanding, as if it were as good a Creed as the Apoſtles Creed, being indeed no Creed, but a prayer: for it is part of the Letany, which is nothing but prayers at which all are enjoyned to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48966:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> kneele Therefore they are excemmunicated <hi>ipſo facto</hi> by the 5. Canon, as depravers of the booke of Common prayer and the Articles of religion.</p>
            <p>36. They offended in burning of Wax-candels, in exceſſive number, two or three hundred at a time, when and where there was no uſe of lights, as namely on Candlemas day 1627. when the daies were length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned two houres, and Service might be done an houre before day light was gon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as it was in <hi>Weſtminſter-Abbey</hi> this yeere 1641. no Candles being lighted there at Evening prayer.</p>
            <p>37. They offended likwiſe in turning their f ces to the Eaſt, and orcing the people ſo to doe. which is a Ceremony not allowed in our Church: in this Doctor <hi>Coſins</hi> offended, not onely in turning the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Deske at morning prayer, and the Deanes Pue, that they could not ſit with their backs towards the Eaſt; but alſo when he adminiſt ed the Communion, he ſtood on the Weſt ſide of the Table with his face towards the Eaſt, and backe towards the people; which is a Ceremony the Popes Prieſts are enjoyned to uſe at Maſſe, and the care of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of our Church was, that Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhould not be like Maſſe-prieſts, in ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, or that our holy C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſhould be like their Idolatrous Maſſe. Again the turning of faces alwaies Eaſtward in the Service of God, is a Ceremony not appointed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor mentioned in the Booke of Common prayer, as Biſhop <hi>Harſnet</hi> confeſſed openly upon the Bench at <hi>Yorke;</hi> and conſequently it is forbidden by the Act of uniformity under great penalty.</p>
            <p>The Prebendaries of <hi>Durham</hi> incurred the horrible ſinne of perjury in not conventing me before the Chapter there to be examined and matters debated, if they had any thing to lay to my charge, according to the Statutes in that behalf, and their oath.</p>
            <q>The words in the ſecond Chapter are theſe:</q>
            <p>38. <hi>In exceſſibus corrigendis decani &amp; Canonicorum eaeſt prerogativa qued ratione Prabendarum non convenieutur extra capitulum, quia cauſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>di queratione Prabendarum emergunt, in capitulo decani &amp; capituli judicio terminari debent,</hi> Such is the prerogative of the Deane and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, that all faults among them muſt be judged by the Deane and Chapter, they muſt not be convented by any out of the Chapter-houſe.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48966:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And againe in the third Chapter:</p>
            <q>Si quaevis quaeſtio aut controverſia inter aliques de Capitule <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riatur per Decanum &amp; Capitulum debet terminari.</q>
            <p>And the concluſion is:</p>
            <q>Forenſia enim judicia, fratres ſubire non decet.</q>
            <p>All theſe they have violated in caſting me into the whirlepoole of the High Commiſſion Court at <hi>Durham, London,</hi> and <hi>Yorke,</hi> and therefore I humbly deſire the Right Honourable Houſe of Peeres to finiſh and conclude my cauſe according to the impechment transferred unto their Lordſhips by the honourable Houſe of Commons, whereby ſatisfaction may be made unto me for the exceſſive wrongs and loſſes which I have ſuſtained. By this it appeareth that all controverſies betweens Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, muſt be ended in the Chapter houſe unleſſe the crime be ſo great that the Viſitor muſt examine and correct it; by whom and none elſe, t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e delinquent may be deprived, and not by the Biſhop, uuleſſe, <hi>Idem Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus in offenſa aliqua aut crimine gravi, veluti Haereſi, adulterio, furto, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurio, atqueid genus aliis culpabilis inventus fuerit.</hi> And then ſaith the ſtatute 37. chap. <hi>Fiat ſequeſtratio praebendae, interim dum talis accuſatio coram Epiſcopo viſitatore pendeat.</hi> Now it is well knowne, that the late Biſhop <hi>Howſon</hi> in his Viſitation 1631. and at ſundry other times cleered me, not culpable of any fault, which could deſerve ſo great puniſhment, or any at all. But contrarily did ſay, that Doctor <hi>Coſin</hi> was a factions and ſeditious man, and that he deſerved to be expeld for corrupting the Church Service and Ceremonies. They (Doctor <hi>Coſin</hi> and others) proceeded againſt me maliciouſly and trecherouſly, by a ſtrange and unheard of ſuſpenſion, from comming to <hi>Durham</hi> Church, onely at the ſame time that I kept reſidence contrary to the ſtatutes, which bind me to be preſent in the time of Divine Service every day, and this they did in the midſt of my Reſidence; ſo that I could not come to Church ten daies together, being prohibited by the ſentence of ſuſpenſion, naild up upon my ſtall.</p>
            <p>They are bound by oath to maintaine and cauſe others to maintaine all rights, priviledges, and cuſtomes of the Church, this Law, right, and cuſtome they perjuriouſly violated.</p>
            <p>39. They perfidiouſly and moſt uncharitably conſpired againſt me all of them, not one excepted, not to come to my reſidence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing one and twenty daies, and though they were oft invited, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48966:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> kindly intreated, yet not one of them would once come to my houſe, ſuch a thing was never heard of before. And it is contrary to their Oath, <hi>Omnes probatas &amp; Probandas bujus Eccleſiae conſuetudines obſervabo.</hi> I take my Oath that I will obſerve all approved cuſtomes of the Church.</p>
            <p>40. They made another moſt damnable conſpiracy againſt me in the Chapter-houſe, in ſending letters full of horrible ſlanders and diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call calumniations to Doctor <hi>Laud</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and ſoure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops, which are ſince dead; and this they did many times: one of which Letters I have, full of untruths, making the Biſhops beleeve <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I am an enemy to the Church, a man unſufferable, and that I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt his Majeſties Chappell. All which are moſt falſe and ſome of them knew they were falſe, and therefore they are perjured, and by the ſtatute to be expeld, <hi>Statuimus ut nemo in virtute juramenti Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> praſtiticontra Decanum aut Canonicos, quicquam dicat aut denuntiet, niſi quod verum crediderit, cap.</hi> 40. By vertue of their Oath all are injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſay nothing againſt any Canon, but what they beleeved to be true.</p>
            <p>And this ſending of Letters by Meſſengers hyred on purpoſe was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes on the Churches charges, whereof a good part was mine own <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and in all other ſuite<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt my ſelfe, they uſed my owne mony which is theevery, robbing me, and endevouring to kill me with my owne ſword.</p>
            <p>41. They made a ſequeſtration of all my living, belonging to my Pre<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>. All the Prebendaries then in <hi>Durham</hi> with the Deane, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to belie and ſlander me, (<hi>viz.</hi>) that I preacht <hi>contra pios &amp; ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ritus Edcleſiae in grave p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riculum animae ſuae, &amp;c.</hi> That I preacht a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly and wholſome Ceremonies of the Church, whereas there was not a word ſpoken againſt any approved Ceremony of our Church, but onely againſt unlawfull Innovations condemned by our Church. If they can name any truely, I will looſe my life.</p>
            <p>42. And although <hi>Haec lis nunquam pend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bat coram Epiſcopo viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort,</hi> for Biſhop <hi>Howſon</hi> kept no viſitation till my cauſe was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York</hi> they made that damnable ſequeſtration twice: firſt, before the ſuſpenſion ſealed the 9 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1628. which becauſe they thought to be wrong, they amended that errour with a capitall crime, for ſcraping out the date, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what they would beſide and writing other words or figures in place thereof, they ſealed that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48966:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> falſe ſequeſtration ag tine, contrary to their Oath in theſe words. <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuimus eti m ut Sigillum Commune nunquam albae chartae aut Palinxeſto opponatur ſub poena perjurii &amp; perpetuae amotionis ab ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceleſiae, illius qui oppoſut, &amp; quiad id faciendum conſenſerit, &amp; ad ſatisfaciend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m pro dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisſint obligati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Common ſeale muſt not be put to ſcrape parchment under the paine of perjury, and expulſion out of the Church of Durham, and the muſt be bound to make ſatisfaction, for the wrong done.</p>
            <p>Theſe treacherons Durhamers, Doctor <hi>Coſin,</hi> Mr. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes,</hi> with their fellowes were not content with their Vill<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nous caſting me into the whirlepoole of the high Commiſſion, where I have been coſt from Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham to London, from London to York, from priſon to priſon, more then 13. yeares together, and utterly undone by their barbarous, more then Turkiſh and Paganiſh Practiſes.</p>
            <p>They were not content I ſay, to plague me with all manner of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments the mercileſſ: Commiſioners could inflict upon me, in all the foreſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id places, but in the Chipter houſes they would bite me, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate my cauſe before it came to tryall, with a malitious ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my living twiſe ſealed in the comp ſſe of one moneth, and that perfidiouſly and ſl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nrdrouſly fraughted with diabolicall calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations.</p>
            <p>They perjuriouſly have offended in detaining from me all that I have loſt theſe 14 yeares ſince 1628 with above 1200. pound, which I have ſpent ſiucethis Parliament began in maintaining witneſſes, &amp;c. whileſt they maintaine their witneſſes. as they have done all their ſuits of law againſt me upon the Church coſt, and by the ſtatutes of Durham Church, which they tooke their Corporall Oathes to obey, they are bound to pay to me, as appeares by the 14. and 15 Chapters.</p>
            <p>If any Prebendary be abſent from Durham Church, being hindred by any lawfull impediment, and namely by impriſonment, he ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all profits, and commodities ariſing any wayes from his Prebend, as if he had all that time beene preſent.</p>
            <p>The words of the ſtatute are theſe. <hi>Quod ſi ob aliquod illorum impedime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enterum</hi> (viz. <hi>profectionem ad Parliamentum &amp; moram ibidem, Incarcerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem non voluntarium &amp;c.) iliquem Canonicorum abeſſe ab eccleſia hac comingerit, in omnibus tamen commodis &amp; emolumintis, ration<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> corporis
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48966:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> prabenda ſua, &amp; quotidianarum diſtributionum, a dicta eccleſia percipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, pro praeſente haberi volumut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Peter Smart</hi> one of the Prebendaries have beene abſent from the Church of Durham 12. yeares, I have beene all that time <hi>Ligiteme impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus:</hi> for I have beene by my falſe brethrens fault and procurement impriſoned, and by wrongfull excommunication, ſuſpenſion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation as is adjudged by the high Court of Parliament, kept from my houſe and Church, and all my meanes, hath beene taken from me, the ſum of all which amounted to above 14000. pound, a great part of which I ſhould have recovered of Doctor <hi>Carre</hi> and his heires, which becauſe the Deane and Chapter hinder me from obtaining, being mine owne, which hee wrongfully got and poſſeſſed, I am to have it of the Deane and Chapter of Durham, and by their oath they are bound and muſt pay it me, beſides ſatisfaction, they muſt make for other wrongs they have done to me and mine.</p>
            <p>They perfidiouſly granted the regiſters office to <hi>Thomas Bullock,</hi> and <hi>Abraham Clarke,</hi> there being a Chapter Act for my Sonne <hi>William Smart,</hi> to ſucceed Mr. <hi>Browne</hi> according to his petition, granted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a great Chapter day, themſelves perſwading mee to take him from the univerſitie to put him to the Inns of Court, and to make him a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry publique, which being done, they being offended with mee for withſtanding their Popiſh innovations in the Church, treacherouſly beguiled my ſaid ſonne to his great loſſe and undoing, and they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Mr. <hi>Browne,</hi> who enjoyed the ſaid office, to ſell the ſame to the ſaid <hi>Bullocke,</hi> and <hi>Clarke,</hi> contrary to a Chapter Act, expreſly forbidding him to ſell it, but to leave it to the Chapters free gift, as he freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, they committed a double perjury in this, firſt in making two Regiſters put joyntly in one patent, whereas by ſtatute &amp; cuſtome, there muſt be but one regiſter, and in ſwearing <hi>Bullock,</hi> and not <hi>Clarke;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expreſſe words of the ſtatute. <hi>Omnes prater pueros jurabunt.</hi> All members of tge Church except <hi>Boies,</hi> muſt take their oath.</p>
            <p>46 They made a leaſe to Mr. <hi>Toby Blaxton,</hi> for the uſe of Mr. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin of hay ground belonging to mee, which I had enjoyed many yeares, by cuſtome of the Church as ten prebendaries alwayes have done, they made a leaſe (I ſay) of that, which by cuſtome only uſeth to be holden, and not by leaſe, which is manifeſt perjury, of which no preſident can be ſhewed, never any leaſe was heard of before to be made in that kind.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48966:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>47 They prejuriouſly offended in making to the ſaid Coſin a leaſe of the Tith Corne of Pittington, allotted to the 4. Prebend, which was mine.</p>
            <p>They granted likewiſe to Doctor <hi>Carre,</hi> a leaſe of my Tyth Corne of Shadforth, belonging to the 4. Prebend.</p>
            <p>They perfidiouſly wrought meanes to put me out of my living, and brought in Doctor <hi>Carr,</hi> who had got in the ſpace of 11. yeares, above 4000. pound out of my livings, which they doe all they can to keepe from me, though the Parliament acquitted me of all cenſures, whereby it is manifeſt, that Doct. <hi>Carre</hi> was never prebendary of Durham the 4. Prebend, which was mine, being never actually void.</p>
            <p>48 The ſtatutes of the Church, <hi>viz. Cap.</hi> 17. have theſe words. <hi>Volumus ut ſingulis Anni terminis ſtipendia omnia tam Decano &amp; Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis quam aliis Miniſtris, numrecentur, &amp; ſolvantur,</hi> And againe <hi>Statui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; ordinamus; ut Theſaurarius qui pro tempore fuerit ſtipendia omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a prout ſtatutis noſtris aſſignantur tempore ſuo numeret &amp; perſolvat, &amp; illa etiam quae ſub anni exitum pro Communi dividenda ſunt ſolvenda. Stat. cap. 22, De officio Theſaur.</hi> Theſe clauſes of the ſtatutes, ſome of the treaſurers have not obſerved, as well in not paying where it was due, as alſo in paying where it was not due, where both the ſtatutes and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Church forbid them to pay, and as I underſtand, they have made Chapter Acts againſt me, to keepe me and mine from my owne, they conſpired altogether to be perjured, and to divide my moneyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Duncon</hi> late treaſurer of Durham, refuſeth to pay me the ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends belonging to my prebend, which were unpaid to Doctor <hi>Carre,</hi> amounting to the ſum of about 40. pound, and neither he nor Doctor <hi>Nayler</hi> now treaſurer, will pay to <hi>William Withrington</hi> my ſervant the ſtipend due to him, though by their oath they are bound to pay ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends <hi>Decano &amp; Canonitis &amp; aliis Miniſtris,</hi> whereof he is one to the Deane and Cannons and other officers whereof he is one.</p>
            <p>49 Yet the moſt prophane Epicuriſme, and Sacralegious implety of the Deane and Prebendaries appeareth in beſtowing of Church livings with charge of ſoules, of which if they be very commodious, they will accept of themſelves, as Doctor <hi>Cradock</hi> did North Allerton worth 200. pound <hi>per annum,</hi> having above 600. pound <hi>per annum</hi> before hee tooke it, not to preach therenor reſide upon it, being Biſhop <hi>Neales</hi> Chancellor, Prebend of Durham, and Vicar of Gain<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord (for he never preacht there nor miniſtred the Sacraments, nor ſaid ſervice) but to ſell
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48966:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> it, for 500. pound, which the miniſter that bought it, held but two yeares till <hi>Cradock</hi> dyed, afterward Mr. <hi>Blaxton</hi> got the ſame North-Allerton having a Prebend of Durham, and parſonage of Sedgefield worth 800. pound <hi>per annum</hi> at which living he never preacht for 16. yeares nor ſaid ſervice, being luſty and able enough to doe any thing, ſaving the duties of his calling.</p>
            <p>This man reſigned and bargained away many livings; Woodhorne, Red Marſhall, his Arch-Deaconry of Yorke to his Sonne in law Doctor Coſin, his Prebend of Yorke, and Vicaridge of Allerton to his Sonne <hi>Thomas Blaxton,</hi> and laſtly his rich perſonage of Sedgefield and Prebend of Durham to his Sonne <hi>Robert Blaxton,</hi> both worth 800. pound <hi>por annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>50 Of all other, their execrable impiety, is ſeene in committing the charge of ſoules to them that they know are uncapable, as namely <hi>Witton Gilbert,</hi> to <hi>Joſeph Cradock;</hi> the foreſaid Doctor <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> Sonne, who was not full miniſter, nor yet is, neither did he ever preach, or ſay Service there; not long after, they gave to the ſame <hi>Ioſeph Cradock</hi> another called Walſend, worth about 60. pound <hi>per annum,</hi> where likewiſe he never officiated, but preſently he ſold them both, one to <hi>Henry Hutton</hi> Clerke, and the other to Sir <hi>Nicholas Tempeſt</hi> for 220. pound, after theſe two he got a third living called <hi>Middleton George,</hi> where he never did any ſervice nor liveth there, but with the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney he got for theſe places, hee bought a Commiſſary ſhip, of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond in Yorkeſhire, whereof he hath made extraordinary great profit, whereby divers complaints have beene made againſt him.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they have given to <hi>William Smith</hi> a Minor Cannon, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caridge Edlingeham, about 40. miles from Durham, contrary to the ſtatute in the 24. Chap. that the benefice muſt not bee above twenty foure miles from Durham, where he ſeldome or never commeth, nor keepeth a ſufficient Curate.</p>
            <p>But they refuſe to collate upon one Maſter <hi>Carwardine</hi> a painfull preacher, the Vicaridge of Aycliffe, which by the order and cuſtome of the Church, I <hi>Peter Smarth</hi> Senior Reſidentiary, have preſented him unto having right ſo to doe, as was proved this Parliament, by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of two witneſſes, and they keepe in a deboyſt and ſcandalous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, one <hi>George Leake,</hi> as appeares by a petition, at this time preferr'd to the Lords of the Parliament, by the pariſhioners there.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48966:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>OF all the aforeſaid Fifty Superſtitious Innovations, in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and Ceremonies of irregularities, and tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Articles of Religion, Injunctions, Rubricks, Cannons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now let us take a view and ſee, of which amongſt the 50. I, or my accuſers and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Durham, London,</hi> and <hi>Yorke</hi> are moſt guilty, and deſerve more to be puniſhed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Innovators in <hi>Durham,</hi> contrarie to the Injunction, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Altars to be removed, and Communion Tables ſet up: have done quite otherwiſe, they have caſt out of the Church lawfull Tables, and brought in unlawfull Altars.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They have left the language of their Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in uſing the word Altar, and leaving Table.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Inſtead of a decent Table, they have ſet up a brave and ſumptuous Altar, with much Superſtitious and unlawfull Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Inſtead of a Wooden Table, ſtanding on a Frame, they made a Stone Altar, on a Wall, or St one Pillars, and conſequently heavie and unmovable, wheras it ſhould be light and portable, that it might be removed as occaſion requireth.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The Rubricke commands the Communion Table be placed where Morning Prayer, and Evening Prayer are appointed to be ſaid, that is in the body of the Church or Chancell: but they place their Altars at the Eaſt end of their Chancells or Quires, where Evening Prayer is never ſaid, nor all Morning Prayer, ſo that the People cannot well heare, nor be ſo well edified.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Our Church commands that the Miniſter Officiating, ſhall ſtand at the North-ſide of the Table, but they ſet up Altars or Tables Altar-wiſe, along by the Wall, with neither ſide toward the North.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Our Lyturgie, and all our Church Books uſe conſtantly the words Miniſter, Sacraments, Communion Table: but our <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamors,</hi> and <hi>Yorkers</hi> ſay falſly, that the words Altar, Sacrifice, Prieſt, are indifferently uſed in our Lyturgie, where indeed they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48966:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> are never uſed, only in the Rubricks Prieſt is uſed ſomtimes, never in the Text: Miniſter is uſed alwayes in the Text, and ſomtimes in the Rubricks.</p>
               <p n="8">8 They preferre Altars, Prieſts, Sacrifices, before Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Tables, Miniſters, Sacraments alleadging falſly that the Fathers of the Primitive Church did ſo. I ſay the learned Divines that reformed the church of <hi>England,</hi> rejected many things, which ſome of the Fathers erroneouſly maintained, as namely this of Altar, Prieſt, Sacrifice, and our learned Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> ſaith the ſame, That their libertie of Speech, occaſioned in Romaniſts that prodigall error in Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="9">9 They removed the Font from place to place, from the Eaſt end of the Church to the Weſt end, from the North to the South, where lately it ſtood. I ſay, with the Injunction, the Font muſt not be removed, and 81 Cannon, the Font ſhall ſtand in the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent uſuall place.</p>
               <p n="10">10 They adored their brave Altar, making legges to it, and bowing down their bodies oftentimes, and profoundly before it, more then ever the Papiſts uſe to doe: I ſay the Table is as holy as the Altar, yet none make legges to the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble when it ſtands as the Church appoints, in the body of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In theſe 10. points concerning Altars, judge rightly ô Biſhop and High Commiſſioner, who maintains the truth? who obeyes the Laws and orders of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>they that did all things wrong, or I that oppoſed my ſelfe lawfully againſt their unlawfull Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; yet you have condemned me only for doing my duty. But did you ever puniſh the wrong doers mine adverſaries? did you ever call them in queſtion? did you amend any thing that was done amiſſe in the Church? No verily, but you have aſſiſted, cheriſhed, and rewarded them with great preferments; you have joyned with them in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me with all rigour and extremitie. As for example, Doctor</hi> Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, <hi>one of my ſpightfulleſt perſecutors hath written a Treatiſe call'd</hi> A Determination in defence of Altars, and bowing down before Altars, <hi>which is a Ceremonie not allow'd by the Church of</hi> England, <hi>but forbidden by the Act of Parliament for uniformitie: yet he proveth it by many fooliſh reaſons, amongſt which this is a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48966:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> principallone,</hi> the Altar is the moſt holything the Church of God hath, therfore it muſt devoutly be bowed unto. <hi>His words are theſe, or to this effect;</hi> Sanctitas, &amp; excellentia Altaris prae reliquis omnibus in Eccleſia: <hi>and againe,</hi> Altare eſt optima, praecipua &amp; ſanctiſſima pars univerſae ſupellectilis Eccleſiaſticae. <hi>The ſanctitie, the excellencie of the Altar above all other things in the Church. The Altar is the beſt, the nobleſt, the holyeſt part of all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ſtuffe or implements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And againe thus he writeth,</hi> The Latine Worthies (Heroes) <hi>terme it</hi> Sacrum, Sanctum, Venerandum Altare, <hi>ſacred, holy, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Altar: and they make compariſon ſaith he,</hi> Inter Altare apud Chriſtianos, et Sanctum Sanctorum apud Judaeos, illudq multis nominibus praeferunt.</p>
               <p>Hinc etiam eſt quod Altaria ſeptis et cancellis, undiqua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> munire et vallare conſueverunt: ne laicorum aliquis propius quam par eſt, ad Altare? ccederet.</p>
               <p>Heroes ſcilicet; <hi>rather Blasphemous wretches, which dare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their falſe Imaginary, Idolized Altar, ſet up in Churches by Antichriſtian Prieſts, in the place of Gods holy Table, compare it I ſay, and in many reſpects preferre it alſo before the</hi> ſanctum ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>of the Iewes, the inward moſt holy Sanctuary, into which the High-Prieſt alone might goe, and that no more then once in a whole yeare: read what Saint</hi> Paul <hi>writes,</hi> Heb. 9. 2, 3. <hi>to the</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And as the moſt holy inward Sanctuary, where the Arke of the Covenant, the Tables of the Law, the 10 Commandements,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were placed, was divided from the outward Sanctuary by a ſecond Vaile, ſo muſt our Prieſts have a holy Chancell parted from the Church, with Railes, and within that Holy, Holy, Holy Sanctuary or Chancell where the Altar that glorious S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at muſt ſtand encloſed with Rails to keep our laiks from aproaching to neer the Sacred</hi> Altar. <hi>Thus much, and twenty times more, writeth Biſhop</hi> Neales <hi>Chaplaine</hi> Duncon, <hi>in juſtification of</hi> Altars, <hi>and</hi> Altar-<hi>cringings. I wonder that none of you Biſhops, Deanes, and arch-Deacons, have taken this</hi> Duncon <hi>with his determination unto examination, that it might be purged with fire, as many better Bookes have bin; I know ſome of you have ſeene it, and peruſed it: The learned Biſhop of</hi> Lincolne, <hi>in his</hi> Holy Table Name and thing, <hi>writes, that lately there came to his hands a certaine Determination concerning</hi> Altars,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48966:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>a Treatiſe well Languaged, but of poore ſtuffe, poor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God knowes, hungry and ragged, naſty and ſcab'd, and ſwarming with loathſome vermine, as by Gods helpe I ſhall make manifeſt to the world here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, if no man elſe will take it in hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>11. The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> commands, that all Monuments of Idol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>try and Superſtition, Images, pictures, paintings, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Crucifixes, Candleſticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be defaced and aboliſhed, that no memory of them remaine in walls, windowes, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Theſe I preached againſt, and for preaching this truth, I have bin perſecuted by them, who inſtead of defacing Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they have given them new faces, bravely painted and guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, inſtead of aboliſhing them, they have multiplied them, and renewed their memory in walls, windowes, copes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>12. They reject the <hi>Homilies,</hi> becauſe they diſallow Images, Altars, and other Superſtitious Ornaments, with Organs and chanting, without underſtanding: I defend the <hi>Homilies,</hi> and the Doctrine of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> taught in them.</p>
               <p>13 They terme their Images, and other Superſtitious trinkets Ornaments of the Church: but I with the Homilies, St. <hi>Bernard</hi> and <hi>Hemingius</hi> ſay they are diſgracements of religion, and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of pietie; they are abominations in the ſight of God, and godly men.</p>
               <p>14 They taking libertie to themſelves to ſet up Altars and Images, and to aboliſh the Sabbath day, the name whereof they cannot endure to heare; have taken away the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments quite out of <hi>Durham</hi> Cathedrall, becauſe the 2. forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Images, the 4. enjoyneth the obſervation of a Sabbath; this they have done contrarie to the expreſſe words of 84. Cannon.</p>
               <p>15 They have uſed Copes, and other ſuperſtitious Veſtments falſly called Copes, at their Altar, when there was no Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and after every Sermon to ſay Prayers in Copes, contrary to the expreſſe words of the Advertiſement, and the 24, 25. Can.</p>
               <p>16. They have Preached, and juſtified him that Preached in the Pulpit, and ſate in his ſtall wearing a Cope, and not a Hood, contrary to the Advertiſement, and the 25 Cannon; and they did Article againſt me, and cenſured me at <hi>Yorke,</hi> for blaming in Mr. <hi>Burgain</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> this notorious irregularitie: but him they excuſed, they never call'd him in queſtion.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48966:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>17 They uſed in <hi>Durham</hi> and ſtill they uſe, not decent, but ſumptuous Copes, embroidered with Images; and they have uſed py-bald, curtaild, ridiculous Veſtme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, even at the adminiſtration of the holy Communion, contrary to the 24. and the latine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. <hi>de officio Decani,</hi> which command decent Copes to be uſed, never but at the Communion: they forbid all Veſtments. <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitione contaminatas,</hi> defiled with Superſtition, that is, ſuch as have Images on them, or have bin uſed at Maſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In theſe 7. points concerning the aboliſhing of the Monuments <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Idolatry, defacing of Images, rejecting the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England <hi>in the Book of Homilies againſt exceſſive coſt upon Organs, Altars, Idols, which falſly they call Ornaments of the Church, being indeed pollutions of Religion, and abominations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In taking out of the Church the Decalogue, becauſe the 2. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement forbids the bowing down to Images, and the 4. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the keeping holy the Sabbath. In uſing Copes at the</hi> Altar, <hi>when there is no Communion, and thoſe not decent, but either raſcall Robe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, very fooles coats or exceeding ſumptuous, glittering with Images: in preaching in a Cope, ſitting in a Stall in a Cope to heare Service, when Copes are forbidden, and Hoods injoyned. In all theſe 7. judge O Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or High Commiſſioner, who is faulty, who tranſgreſſeth the Laws and Orders of the Church? which of us is conformable to the Church of</hi> England? <hi>who deſerves puniſhment, and who ſhould be rewarded? I have obſerved all theſe Laws and Canons, yet I have been puniſhed with all rigour and extremitie: my perſecutors of</hi> Durham <hi>and</hi> York <hi>having broken all Laws of the Church have never been call'd in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; ſome of them have been advanced to high dignities, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Is this Prelaticall Iuſtice? is this Epiſcepall government? ſurely the judges of hell,</hi> Minos <hi>and</hi> Radamanthus <hi>would never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſo injuſt ſentences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>18 The 49 Injunction commandeth that Muſicke be not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church; that the Common Prayer ſhould be worſe underſtood. That there ſhould be modeſt and diſtinct ſinging, to the intent all may be underſtood plainly, and the ſenſe perceived: But <hi>Durhamers</hi> have uſed exceſſive Muſicke, both Inſtrumentall and vocall, even at 6 a clock Prayer in the morning, uſed to be read plainly, and the adminiſtration of Sacraments, wherby thoſe holy actions have been greatly diſturbed.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48966:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 19 The preface to the Communion Book commandeth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thems to be cut off, and Pſalmes are allowed to be ſung before and after Sermons: But our Innovators of <hi>Durham,</hi> have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden all ſinging of Pſalmes, till this laſt yeare 1641. from 1629. all which time no Pſalme hath bin ſung in <hi>Durham</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>20 The <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> hath been ſung, not after the manner of diſtinct reading, that the people might underſtand, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have bin compelled with fighting and brawling to ſtand on their feet, though they could not repeat the ſame <hi>Creed</hi> in an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible voice, as the 18. <hi>Canon</hi> appoints.</p>
               <p>21. They tooke for Aſſiſtants at the Communion, the whole quire men and Children which communicated not, contrarie to the cuſtome and practiſe of all Cathedrall <hi>Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>22 They chaunted or approved him that did ſit in his ſtall, to ſing prick ſong, which both cuſtom and Law forbids Preachers and Praebends to doe; but they would not ſuffer Pſalmes to be ſung, that all the Congregation might ſing with them.</p>
               <p>23 &amp; 24 They took the Morning Prayer at 6 of the clocke quite away for two years together, a moſt impudent Innovation, contrary to all the Cathedralls of <hi>England,</hi> and in this they viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many Lawes and Injunctions, eſpecially the Injunction made by Commiſſioners under the great Seale of <hi>England, prime Eliz.</hi> for the Church of <hi>Durham;</hi> and in ſo doing, they incurd the terrible crime of perjury, becauſe that morning-prayer was eſtabliſhed by Law and cuſtome, which all took their othes that they would obſerve.</p>
               <p>25. They confounded and turned all forenoone ſervices upſide downe, by ſaying the whole ordinary ſervice, with <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> read at ſix of the clocke in the morning, and ſaying a new found ſecond ſervice, without either <hi>Chapters</hi> or <hi>Pſalmes</hi> betweene ten and eleven, the uſuall time in all Churches for the ordinary ſervice to be ſaid.</p>
               <p>26. They removed the ordinary ſervice a whole twelve Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth together from Ten of clocke to eight, and all that time they had three forenoon ſervices: afterwards they placed the ordinary and moſt ſolemne ſervice both Sundayes and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes, in the roome of morning prayer at ſix a clocke, and they called the people thereunto by the ringing of ſix bells, to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48966:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> which not three perſons uſually reſorted, in Winter time eſpecially.</p>
               <p>27. They did not obſerve the time, place, order and faſhion of rights and ceremonies, as the 14. Canon preſcribes, without adding or diminiſhing any thing in matter or forme.</p>
               <p>28. They ſaid evening prayer in the accuſtomed place alwayes: but the Altar at the Eaſt end of the Quire where they ſaid their ſecond ſervice, is no accuſtome d place for any ſervice; but it is an Innovation in <hi>Durham,</hi> begun by Biſhop <hi>Neals</hi> Chaplains.</p>
               <p>29 They made Chancels within Chancels, contrary to the <hi>Rubrick.</hi> which ſaith chancels ſhall remaine as they were in times paſt: a ſtrange <hi>Innovation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>30 The Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> commands all <hi>Churches</hi> to be Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, but <hi>Durham Cathedrall</hi> was agreeable to none in their forenoone <hi>Services.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>31 No rite, order, forme or manner of ſaying <hi>Mattens,</hi> may be uſed in <hi>Cathedrall</hi> or <hi>Pariſh Churches,</hi> then what is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Booke of <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and if any Perſon compell by deeds or threatnings, to ſay Prayers in any other manner, let him be Indicted, Mr. <hi>Coſin</hi> and his Aſſociates have tranſgreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this clauſ of the <hi>act</hi> for uniformity, oftentimes notoriouſly</p>
               <p>32 They ſuffer not the Preacher to diſmiſſe the Congregation, but the Sermon being done he comes downe from the Pulpit, and another goeth to the Communion Table, and having ſaid 2, or 3 Prayers, he ſaith <hi>the Peace of God,</hi> and the People depart, which is grounded upon a <hi>Rubricke</hi> miſunderſtood.</p>
               <p>33 They have ſpoken, and Preached againſt the Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, terming the Reformation of our Church a deforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Reformers ignorant <hi>Calviniſticall Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>34 They tooke upon them to make new Orders for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of unlawfull Services and Ceremonies, for which they are Excommunicated.</p>
               <p>And they have given to the Biſhops tranſcendent Authoritie in ordering Church matters, which notwithſtanding is limited by the locall Statutes of <hi>Durham</hi> Church, and by the Cannons, his Office is to Preach, and not to hinder Preaching &amp;c.</p>
               <p>35 They make <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> a fourth <hi>Creed,</hi> and therefore they injoyn the Ceremonie of ſtanding, which is a Prayer, and a part of the Letany, at which all muſt kneele.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48966:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>36 They lighted on <hi>Candlemas</hi> Day more then 200 waxe Candles, when none were needfull, the day being lengthened 2 houres, the 2 of <hi>February</hi> being equall to the 18. of <hi>October.</hi> St. <hi>Lukes,</hi> on which Day no <hi>Church</hi> lighted <hi>Candles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>37 They conſtantly obſerve that unlawfull Ceremonie of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faces to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> not allowed by the Church, and ſome when they officiate at the Communion Table, looke toward the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> turning their backs to the <hi>People,</hi> after the manner of <hi>Maſſe Prieſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In theſe 20. from 17 to 37. mine Adverſaries of</hi> Durham <hi>have offended, they have violated above 40. Orders,</hi> Cannons. Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Rubrickes, <hi>not onely in Ceremonies, but in the moſt ſubſtantiall parts of Gods Service and Sacraments. yet which of them was ever puniſhed, convented or Queſtioned before a Biſhop or other Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall judge for ſo great and ſo many preſumptuous irregularities, and Innovations which have <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>throwne the whole frame of our Church Diſcipline, and Gouernment: I, that to my knowledge have Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in nothing, I that oftentimes offered the Comiſſioners Biſhop</hi> Harſnet <hi>and his Colleagues which cenſured me ſo cruelly; that if they would ſhew me my error, and in what I offended againſt the Church of</hi> ENGLAND <hi>in Doctrine or Ceremonie, I would amend and make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: But it is great Tyranny and Div<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lliſh oppreſſion to kill a true Man, unleſſe he will betray Truth, and renounce his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O ye Biſhops and other Spirituall Iudges, how terrible have you been in deſtroying painfull Preachers, for not obſerving the Croſſe in Baptiſme and other trifling Ceremonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But theſe monſtrous Hell hounds of</hi> Durham <hi>and Yorke, thoſe Popiſh, Hereticall, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rminian, Schiſmaticall Innovators, and moſt pernitious corruptors of Religion amongſt us: you let them ſcape, nay ſome of you have abetted and aſſiſted them unperſecuting me and others living peaceably amongſt you: you help theſe Enemies of God to afflict and vexe me: you honour and reward Wolves, and make them ſtrong to worry Chriſts Sheepe and Lambs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. O Lord God to whom Vengeance belongeth, thon GOD to whom Vengeance belongeth, ſhew thy ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Ariſe thou Iudge of the World, and reward the proud after their deſervings, and ſo forth to the 6 <hi>Verſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48966:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
